A Finding Aid to the Fred Mitchell Papers, 1938-2007, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mitcfred
Archives of American Art
- Subject Files, 1943-2007; Series 5; 6 Linear feet Boxes 6-12
  - Pricing of Works of Art, 1976-1990 (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - Queens College, 1973-1981; undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Ramirez, Carlos, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations -- Letters from Special Friends, Usually in Reference to Exhibitions or Expectations, 1952-1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations and References, 1980-1986; undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Reeves, Paul, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Reproduction of Paintings, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Restoration of Paintings, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Reunions, Meridian High School and Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1992; 1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Reviews, undated; 1950s-2001 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Reyher, Tobias, 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Rich, Garry, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Rogers, George, 1960; 1997 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Roko Gallery, Ithaca, New York, 1970-1973 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Rooney, Peter ("Petrus"), undated; 1958-1995 (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
  - Ruddick, Gary, 1959-1966 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Sager, Chris and Family, undated; 1966-1989 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Selmowitz, Abram, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Schloss, Edith, 1970s-1980 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Schmit, Gladys, 1943-1944 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Schuyler, James, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Sepeshy, Zoltan, undated; 1960-1973 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Silvermine Lecture, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Smith, Irene, undated; 1985-1995 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Sokolowski, Linda, 1979-1982 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Stamos, Theodoros, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - State University of New York, Binghamton -- Fred Mitchell Exhibition (1993 November 12 - 1993 November 29) (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - State University of New York, Binghamton -- Teaching, undated; 1975-1983 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - State University of New York, Binghamton -- University Art Gallery, Acting Director, 1967-1977 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - State University of New York, New Paltz, undated; 1978-1986 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - State University of New York, Stony Brook, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Stevens, John W. ("Dicky"), 1965-1994; undated (Box 11, Folder 32-33)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Stonewall, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Strauss, Jonathan and Beth, in Alaska, 1980s-1990s (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Streeter, Middy, 1976-1983; undated (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Strickland, John ("Giovanni"), 1964-1987; undated (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Sultz, Phil and Family, 1956-2006; undated (Box 11, Folder 39-42)
  - Tabakman Gallery, "Group Show 1999" (1999 January 5-1999 January 31), 1998-1999 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - The Tanager Gallery, 1983; undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Tenth Street Days: The Co-ops of the 50's" (1977 December 20 -- 1978 January 7) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bob Tomlinson Gallery, undated; 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Tormented," Part I, circa 1970s; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Universal Limited Art Editions, Inc., 1990-1991 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - University of Maine, Machias, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - University of North Carolina, Greensboro, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - University of Oregon, 1983-1984 (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
  - Venice, 1965-1988 (Box 12, Folder 11-13)
  - Vicente, Esteban, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Mark Vinson and Fred Mitchell Solo Exhibitions, White Box Gallery (1997 November 7 -- 1997 November 29) (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Ward, Jeffrey, 1970s (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Ward, Sandra, undated; 1972-1989 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Waring, Jimmy, 1963-1978; undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Watercolor Painting, 1960s-circa 1990s (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - West Broadway Gallery, "Heart Attack" (1994 February 1 -- 1994 March 15) (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - White, Ed, 1956; undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Windley, Carlyle, 1969-1978 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Winn, Kitty, 1970s-1986 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Wisconsin State University Platteville, 1965-1970 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Wise, Barbi and Howard, undated; 1959-1989 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Howard Wise Gallery, 1954-1965; undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Wittgenstein, Ludwig - The Duty of Genius by Ray Monk, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Wojnarowicz, Daniel, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Wong, Martin, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Yeomans, Marion, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Zogbaum, Rufus, undated; 1973-1981 (Box 12, Folder 31)
- Artwork, circa 1940s-2002; Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 12-13
  Artwork by Mitchell consists mainly of drawings and sketches in ink and pencil. Many identified and dated. Some were done while traveling and others are studies for paintings. Also found are 4 abstract watercolors. Artwork by others includes drawings in pencil, ink, pastels and watercolors by Peter Rooney, students, and unidentified artists.
  Artwork by Mitchell is arranged by medium and filed alphabetically by folder title; artwork by others in arranged in the same manner.
  - By Mitchell (Box 12)
    - Drawings, undated; circa 1940s-2002 (Box 12, Folder 32-41)
    - Drawings, Andrew, undated (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - Drawings, All the Way Across II, Flying Westward, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - Drawings, Around 57th Street, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Drawings, Buddhist Fresco, undated (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - Drawings, Hawaii, circa 1984 (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - Drawings, Italy, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 47)
    - Drawings, Middy Triptych Studies, 1990-1992; undated (Box 12, Folder 48)
    - Drawings, Northern-Edging, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Drawings, Out into Space We Go, 1988-1990 (Binder 13, Folder 2)
    - Drawings, The Pantheon, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Drawings, Remotion, undated; 1981-1994 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Drawings, Sojourning, 1964; 1980; undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Drawings, Spirit of Zattere, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Drawings, Story Illustrations, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Drawings, Triptych Possibilities, 1990-1992; undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Watercolors, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - By Others (Box 13)
    - Drawings by Peter Rooney, 1972-1982; undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Drawings by Unidentified Artists, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Watercolors by Students and Unidentified Artists, 1987-1984; undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Sketchbooks, 1955-1993; Series 7; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 13, 15
  The series consists of 16 sketchbooks containing sketches and drawings in pencil, ink, and marker; a few are embellished with color. In addition, there are a small number of finished watercolors and one pastel. Subjects include figures, portraits, landscapes, harbor views, birds, and abstract compositions. Many sketches and drawings are identified and dated.
  Volumes are numbered chronologically. Many volumes represent a single year. However, some years filled more than one volume, a few volumes include several years, and some contain overlapping dates.
  - Volume 1, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Volume 2, "'Portrait of a Queen,' also Julie Morris on TV", undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Volume 3 and Volume 4, undated (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Volume 5, "Chenango, Binghamton, Susquehanna", undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Volume 6, undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Volume 7, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Volume 8, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Volume 9 and Volume 10, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Volume 11, Anatomical Studies, 1974-1975; Oversized material housed in Box 15 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Volume 12, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Volume 13, 1983 (Binder 13, Folder 23, Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Volume 14, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Volume 15, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Volume 16, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Sketchbook, Volume 11, Anatomical Studies (from Box 13, Folder 23), 1974-1975 (Box 15)
- Printed Material, 1938-2004; Series 8; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 13-14
  This series includes a wide variety of printed material about or mentioning Mitchell, concerning friends, general art topics and other subjects of interest to him. Included are exhibition catalogs and announcements, magazine articles, newspaper clippings, promotional material from organizations, and concert programs.
  Printed material is arranged in rough chronological order. Additional printed material is enclosed with correspondence (Series 2), loose letters are found in some diaries (Series 4), and many subject files (Series 5) include significant amounts of printed material.
  - Printed Material, 1938-1960s; undated (Box 13, Folder 27-31)
  - Printed Material, 1970s-2004 (Box 14, Folder 1-9)
- Photographs, 1940s-2002; Series 9; 0.5 Linear feet Box 14
  Photographs of Fred Mitchell include portraits and candid views; he also appears with friends, students, and family members. There are images of his siblings and their respective families, as well as of Don Wright and unidentified individuals. Artwork documented in this series is mainly by Mitchell; also, there are photographs of works by Lois Dodd, William Freed, Hans Hofmann, George Preston, and Philip Sultz. Views of exhibition installations and openings record some of Fred Mitchell's solo exhibitions; views of group shows include some in which his sister, Elizabeth Pajerski, participated. Pictures of places include travel photographs.
  Photographs are categorized by subject - people, artwork, exhibition installations and openings, and places - and within each group, arrangement is alphabetical. Additional photographs are enclosed with correspondence (Series 2) and are included in many subject files (Series 5).
  - People (Box 14)
    - Fred Mitchell, 1940s-2002 (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
    - Fred Mitchell at Art Students League (Eben Thompson, photographer), circa 1990s (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Fred Mitchell with Others, undated; 2002 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Mitchell Family (Mother, Fred, Robert Lyle, Elizabeth), undated; 1957-1967 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Thomas Lyle Mitchell and Family (Marie, Tommy, Jimmy), 1950s-1986 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Elizabeth Mitchell Pajerski and Family (Fred, Frank), undated, 1958-1995 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Don Wright and Unidentified Individuals, undated; 1964 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Artwork by Mitchell (Box 14)
    - Paintings, 1961-1989; undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Paintings owned by Harold, undated (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Sculpture, 1960; undated (Box 14, Folder 20-21)
    - Watercolors, undated (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Watercolors, Southern Tip Series, circa 1979 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Artwork by Others (executed 1950s-1980s), undated (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Installations and Openings (Box 14)
    - Horne-Marshall Gallery, Meridian, Mississippi, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Lincoln Center Show, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Thomas McCormick Gallery, Chicago, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - White Box Gallery, Philadelphia, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified Venues, 1997; undated (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Places (Box 14)
    - Hawaii Trip with Sandra Ward, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Italy -- Fiesole, Positano, Rome and Venice, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Old Mitchell Homestead, Ellistown, Mississippi, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - View from Ferry, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 33)
      Note on envelope indicates "Photograph from the ferry made by Beth in June of '86 --the Southern Tip School of Art"
    - Wall-South Neighborhood just Before Destruction of my Studio, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified, undated; 1989 (Box 14, Folder 35)